<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<elements>
  <info>
    <name>All Beneath the Yonder Seas and Streams — Subclasses</name>
    <description>All subclass options from ABYSS, mapped to Aurora archetypes.</description>
    <update version="1.0.0">
      <file name="abyss-subclasses.xml" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/SageZeMage/aurora-abyss/main/abyss-subclasses.xml" />
    </update>
  </info>
  <element name="Defiler" type="Archetype" source="ABYSS" id="ID_ABYSS_ARCH_artificer_Defiler">
    <supports>Artificer Specialist</supports>
    <description>Defiler (ABYSS)

### Level 3: Defiler
A Defiler is a master of deadly substances both caustic and corruptive, using foul mixtures to create sickeningly permanent effects. Any battlefield a Defiler enters is hauntingly marked with cruel magic that scars the landscape and mutilates its victims. Valued for scorched-earth warfare, members of the specialization are summoned when morals and long-term consequences no longer matter.

### Level 3: Bonus Proficiencies
When you adopt this specialization at 3rd level, you gain proficiency with the poisoner's kit, and can use it as a spellcasting focus for your artificer spells. If you already have this proficiency, you gain proficiency with one other type of artisan's tools of your choice.

### Level 3: Defiler Spells
Starting at 3rd level, you always have certain spells prepared after you reach particular levels in this class, as shown in the Defiler Spells table. These spells count as artificer spells for you, but they don't count against the number of artificer spells you prepare.

### Level 3: Tainted Ground
At 3rd level, you learn to magically salt the earth around you, corrupting it and sickening creatures that enter the contaminated area. As an action, you can use a poisoner's kit to befoul a 10-foot cube you can see within 60 feet of you, choosing one of the options listed below. The area becomes corrupted for 1 minute, until you use this feature again, or until it is dispelled by a dispel magic spell. An area affected by this feature remains forever scarred and unable to support any kind of plant or animal life after the effect ends. You are immune to the effects of Tainted Ground that you create.

Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest, unless you expend a spell slot of 1st level or higher to use it again.

At the start of each of your turns, the corruption spreads to one adjacent 10-foot cube of your choice. The new cube must have at least one face adjacent to another cube of Tainted Ground, and has the same effect as it.

 Foul, heavy smoke fills the area, scouring the eyes and lungs and lightly obscuring the area. When a creature enters the area for the first time on a turn or starts its turn there, it takes 1d6 acid damage and must succeed on a Constitution saving throw against your artificer spell save DC or become blinded until the start of its next turn. This damage increases when you reach higher levels in this class, to 2d6 at 5th level, 3d6 at 9th level, and 4d6 at 15th level.

 Sticky black tar fills the area, coating any objects not being worn or carried within it. For every 1 foot a creature moves through this area, it must expend 4 feet of movement. When a creature enters the area for the first time on a turn or starts its turn there, it takes 1d6 necrotic damage. This damage increases when you reach higher levels in this class, to 2d6 at 5th level, 3d6 at 9th level, and 4d6 at 15th level.

 Intense supernatural flames burn within the area, igniting flammable objects in the area that aren't being worn or carried. When a creature enters the area for the first time on a turn or starts its turn there, it takes 1d10 fire damage. This damage increases when you reach higher levels in this class, to 2d10 at 5th level, 3d10 at 9th level, and 4d10 at 15th level.

 Sickly bright light fills the area, befouling all it touches. When a creature enters the area for the first time on a turn or starts its turn there, it takes 1d6 radiant damage and must succeed on a Constitution saving throw against your artificer spell save DC or become poisoned until the start of its next turn. This damage increases when you reach higher levels in this class, to 2d6 at 5th level, 3d6 at 9th level, and 4d6 at 15th level.

### Level 5: Creeping Corruption
Starting at 5th level, you can use your Tainted Ground to channel your foul magics. When you cast an artificer spell while standing within an area of Tainted Ground, you choose any point covered by Tainted Ground. The spell is cast as if you were at the chosen point, but you must use your own senses. After you cast a spell of 1st level or higher in this way, you can cause the Tainted Ground to spreads to a number of 10-foot-cubes equal to the spell's level. Each new cube must have at least one face adjacent to another cube of Tainted Ground.

### Level 9: Reduced Casualties
Starting at 9th level, you learn how to protect others from your own powers. When you cast an artificer spell or create an area of Tainted Ground, you can designate any number of creatures you can see to be immune to its effects.

### Level 15: Profane Empowerment
By 15th level, your exposure to horrific pollutants allows you to become one with the contaminants:

Creatures of your choice have resistance to the damage type dealt by your Tainted Ground while standing in it.
If you start your turn within an area of Tainted Ground, your speed is increased by 10 feet until the end of the turn.
When you cast an artificer spell that deals damage while standing in a patch of Tainted Ground, you can choose to change the spell's damage type to the same type that the Tainted Ground deals.</description>
  </element>
  <element name="Path of the Drowned" type="Archetype" source="ABYSS" id="ID_ABYSS_ARCH_barbarian_Path_of_the_Drowned">
    <supports>Primal Path</supports>
    <description>Drowned (ABYSS)

### Level 3: Path of the Drowned
The Path of the Drowned is walked by those who fall into the dark depths of the sea and survive - cast ashore by shipwrecks, attacked by sea monsters, or tossed overboard during terrible storms. Most of these barbarians did not choose this fate. Instead, their all-consuming rage is the legacy of a prolonged brush with death. Some belong to tribes who venerate the power of the sea and willingly give themselves to the waves for a chance at such strength.

Falling somewhere between the living and the dead, barbarians who walk this path remember the rattling of chains and crashing waves when they rage. Their spectral powers control the battlefield around them as they drag their enemies into the cold and crushing depths to suffer their own grim fate.

### Level 3: Flooded Lungs
At 3rd level, you take on certain characteristics that walk the brink of life and death. You gain the following benefits:

You gain a swimming speed of 30 feet.
You are immune the effects of being underwater at a depth greater than 100 feet.
You no longer need to breathe.
You appear dead to spells and magical effects used to determine your status, and are indistinguishable from a corpse while you remain motionless.

### Level 3: Spectral Chains
Also at 3rd level, your memories of the crushing depths cause you to manifest spectral chains that wrap around you or hang off your person. The chains are visible to only you when you are not raging and cannot travel more than 10 feet away from you.

The chains can be used to manipulate an object, open an unlocked door or container, stow or retrieve an item from an open container, or pour the contents out of a vial. The chains cannot perform any task that requires careful handling, attack,  activate magic items, or carry more than 10 pounds.

When your Spectral Chains require a saving throw, the DC equals 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Strength modifier.

### Level 3: Oppressive Haul
When you choose this path at 3rd level, you learn to fully embrace your spectral powers by summoning a ghostly anchor that connects to your chains.

When you enter a rage, you can hurl the anchor at a creature within 30 feet of you. The creature must succeed on a Strength saving throw or be pulled up to 15 feet in a straight line towards you by your Spectral Chains. While you're raging, you can use a bonus action on your turn to toss the anchor again, targeting the same creature or a different one.

### Level 6: Heave-To
Beginning at 6th level, you can cause your Spectral Chains to bind and harm your foes. When a creature fails its save against your chains, its speed is halved until the start of your next turn. In addition, the creature takes 1d6 cold damage.

When you reach certain levels in this class, the damage dealt by your chains increases: 2d6 at 10th level and 3d6 at 14th level.

### Level 10: Dead Men Talking
At 10th level, your connection to the dead is strong enough to contact them directly. When you do so, you cast the speak with dead spell without using a spell slot or material components. Rather than speaking with the corpse's mouth, you see a spectral image of the creature as it was in life hovering above the body.

After you cast the spell in this way, you can't use this feature again until you finish a short or long rest.

### Level 14: Batten Down the Hatches
Starting at 14th level, you can call upon the drowned to restrain the living with your chains. When you take damage from a   creature that is within 5 feet of you, you can use your reaction to wrap that creature in Spectral Chains. The creature must succeed on a Dexterity saving throw or be restrained until the end of your next turn.</description>
  </element>
  <element name="College of Shanties" type="Archetype" source="ABYSS" id="ID_ABYSS_ARCH_bard_College_of_Shanties">
    <supports>Bard College</supports>
    <description>Shanties (ABYSS)

### Level 3: College of Shanties
The College of Shanties is an \"informal\" college, a loose community of tradesmen that work in environments with harsh, repetitive labor. Far from studying theory or undertaking long apprenticeships, a shantyman learns practical skills on the job.

It's a common turn of phrase that \"a good shantyman is worth four extra hands on the rope.\" The bards of this college support their allies by working alongside them and leading by example. They know the perfect tune for every situation, from drinking and carousing (skills they generally excel at) to working and fighting.

### Level 3: Three Sheets to the Wind
When you join the College of Shanties at 3rd level, you gain proficiency with brewer's supplies and you can choose to use a mug or tankard as a spellcasting focus for your bard spells in place of a musical instrument.

Your quick wit has been known to get you both in and out of trouble. You learn the vicious mockery cantrip, which doesn't count against the number of bard cantrips you know. If you already know this cantrip, then you learn a different bard cantrip of your choice.

### Level 3: Blow the Man Down
At 3rd level, you gain the ability to coordinate your allies with raucous songs. As a bonus action, you can expend one use of your Bardic Inspiration to start performing a sea shanty, choosing from one of the following options.

The performance lasts for up to 1 minute or until your concentration ends (as if you were concentrating on a spell), and can be used on any creature that can hear you within 15 feet of you. It ends early if you are incapacitated, become unable to speak, start a new performance, or end it voluntarily (no action required).



 When a creature within range provokes an opportunity attack, you can use your reaction to impose disadvantage on the attack roll.

 When a creature within range makes a melee attack roll and misses, you can use a reaction to allow it to reroll the attack roll against a different target within range.

 When a creature within range makes an ability check, you can use your reaction to add your Charisma modifier to the roll.

 When a creature within range makes a Constitution saving throw to maintain concentration on a spell, you can use your reaction to impose disadvantage on the saving throw.

When a hostile creature within range misses you or an ally with an attack, you can use your reaction to cast vicious mockery, targeting that creature.

The range of your performance improves when you reach certain levels in this class, increasing to 20 feet at 5th level, 25 feet at 10th level, and 30 feet at 15th level.

### Level 6: Know the Ropes
At 6th level, you've learned to keep perfect tempo while you focus on the task at hand. You no longer need to concentrate on your shanty performances.

In addition, you gain the ability to weave your shanties with the disruptive power of your Countercharm ability. While you are performing, any ally in range is affected by your Countercharm. 

### Level 14: Sea Medley
At 14th level, your mastery of the form allows you to seamlessly flow from one song to another. When you start your performance you can choose two options instead of one.

Additionally, while you are performing, each creature of your choice within range gain a bonus to Performance checks equal to your Charisma modifier (minimum  of +1).</description>
  </element>
  <element name="Journey Domain" type="Archetype" source="ABYSS" id="ID_ABYSS_ARCH_cleric_Journey_Domain">
    <supports>Divine Domain</supports>
    <description>Journey (ABYSS)

### Level 1: Journey Domain
The gods of the Journey domain aid travelers in their journeys, guiding them safely to their destinations. These deities are often worshiped at humble shrines along well-traveled roads, but also feature in temples near ports in seaside cities.

At each indicated cleric level, add the listed spells to your spells prepared.

### Level 1: Bonus Proficiencies
When you choose this domain at 1st level, you gain proficiency with martial weapons, land vehicles, and water vehicles.

### Level 1: Imbue Mobility
Starting at 1st level, when you restore hit points to a creature with a spell of 1st level or higher, the target can use its reaction to move up to half its speed without provoking opportunity attacks.

### Level 2: Channel Divinity: Zealous Charge
Starting at 2nd level, you can use your Channel Divinity to imbue divine might into one of your allies.

You can grant speed and strength to a creature you can see within 30 feet of you as a bonus action on your turn. Until the start of your next turn, the creature's speed is doubled, and each creature that it moves within 5 feet of for the first time on a turn during this duration must make a Strength saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes force damage equal to 2d6 + your cleric level and is knocked prone. On a successful save, it takes half as much damage and is not knocked prone.

### Level 6: Long Road Ahead
Starting at 6th level, you can grant up to six creatures you can see temporary hit points equal to half your cleric level + your Wisdom modifier (minimum of 1 hit point) when you finish a short or long rest. While a creature has these hit points, its movement speed increases by 10 feet, and it has advantage on Constitution saving throws made against exhaustion from a forced march.

### Level 8: Divine Strike
At 8th level, you gain the ability to infuse your weapon strikes with divine energy. Once on each of your turns when you hit a creature with a weapon attack, you can cause the attack to deal an extra 1d8 force damage to the target. When you reach 14th level, the extra damage increases to 2d8.

### Level 17: Unchained and Unfettered
Beginning at 17th level, you are always under the effects of the freedom of movement spell, and your movement doesn't provoke opportunity attacks.</description>
  </element>
  <element name="Water Domain" type="Archetype" source="ABYSS" id="ID_ABYSS_ARCH_cleric_Water_Domain">
    <supports>Divine Domain</supports>
    <description>Water (ABYSS)

### Level 1: Water Domain
Gods of the water inhabit many domains, from shining seas to lakes to small forest streams. These gods range from grand deities like Poseidon, Istishia, and Umberlee to small water spirits like Nommos or Astlik.

Clerics of this domain can be found commonly by seas, rivers, or lakes, whether aboard a ship or serving at a temple to bless sailors before their travels. They see the warmth, beauty, and protectiveness of water, and use their abilities to harness it to shelter others.

At each indicated cleric level, add the listed spells to your spells prepared.

For players who don't have access to Xanathar's Guide to Everything, the following lines in the Water Domain Spells table can be replaced:

### Level 1: Divine Lash
When you choose this domain at 1st level, you learn the thorn whip cantrip, which counts as a cleric cantrip for you and doesn't count against the number of cleric cantrips you know. When you cast the spell as a cleric cantrip, its material component is a drop of water, and it gains the hydromancy tag with a hydromancy radius of 60 feet. The whip the spell creates is formed from water.

If you use a drop of holy water as the spell's material component, the spell deals an additional 1d6 radiant damage to fiends and undead.

### Level 1: Sacred Font
Starting at 1st level, you can conjure pure holy water, taken directly from the blessed lakes and rivers of the upper planes. Over a long rest, you can conjure enough holy water to fill a number of flasks equal to your Wisdom modifier (a minimum of one flask). This water lasts until you use it or complete a long rest.

A creature can use an action to drink or administer the holy water as a potion. The target regains a number of hit points equal to 1 + half your cleric level, and becomes cured of one disease or poison affecting it.

### Level 2: Channel Divinity: Water Ward
Starting at 2nd level, you can use your Channel Divinity to release a burst of protective water.

As an action, you douse up to six creatures within 20 feet of you with blessed water. Each creature gains temporary hit points equal to your cleric level + your Wisdom modifier (minimum of 1 hit point), which last for 1 hour. While a creature has these hit points, it can walk on the surface of water as if it were harmless solid ground, has resistance to acid and fire damage, and gains a +1 bonus to AC.

### Level 6: Channel Divinity: Bless Water
Starting at 6th level, you can use your Channel Divinity to impart divine power onto water.

As an action, you present your holy symbol and choose a 20-foot-cube within 30 feet of you. For 1 minute, water in the area becomes imbued with divine energy. When a creature enters the water for the first time on a turn or starts its turn there, it regains 1 hit point if it is not a fiend or undead. A fiend or undead instead takes 2d6 radiant damage.

### Level 8: Potent Spellcasting
Starting at 8th level, you add your Wisdom modifier to the damage you deal with any cleric cantrip.

### Level 17: Rain's Blessing
Starting at 17th level, you can use your action to summon a torrent of rain in a 30-foot-radius, 40-foot-high cylinder, which lasts for 1 minute. When you do so, you can designate any number of creatures you can see to be protected by the rain. While an affected creature is within the area, it has advantage on attack rolls, and attack rolls made against it are at disadvantage.

The rain produces water at a rate of 1 gallon of water per round in each 5-foot square area it covers when it is summoned, and again at the start of each of your turns before it ends. The water extinguishes unprotected flames and forms a puddle in the area.

If you're within 60 feet of the cylinder, you can move it up to 60 feet as a bonus action on your turn.

Once you use this feature, you must finish a long rest before you can use it again.</description>
  </element>
  <element name="Circle of Coral" type="Archetype" source="ABYSS" id="ID_ABYSS_ARCH_druid_Circle_of_Coral">
    <supports>Druid Circle</supports>
    <description>Coral (ABYSS)

### Level 2: Circle of Coral
Druids of the Circle of Coral take inspiration of the ocean and its vibrant reef systems, protecting and safeguarding the creatures of the wild wherever they find them, both within the ocean and without. All life originated from the sea; as such, it is the duty of druids of the circle to protect life wherever they see it, channeling primal magics to bring the power of coral reefs wherever nature has need of it.

### Level 2: Coral Calling
At 2nd level, you can conjure a coral reef around you to harm foes and protect allies. As an action, you can expend a use of your Wild Shape feature to conjure a coral reef, rather than transforming into a beast form. The reef grows in 10-foot radius around you, moves with you, and its area is lightly obscured and difficult terrain. When you conjure the reef, you can designate any number of creatures you can see to be unaffected by the reef. A designated creature also has half cover from effects that originate outside the reef while it is within the reef.

When a creature affected by the difficult terrain enters the reef for the first time on a turn or starts its turn there, it takes 2d4 piercing damage.

The reef lasts for 10 minutes, after which it crumbles into dust. Also, it ends early if you dismiss it as a bonus action, fall unconscious, or use your Wild Shape again.

At 10th level, the reef's radius increases to 20 feet, and the piercing damage increases to 3d4. At 18th level, the reef's radius increases to 30 feet, and the piercing damage increases to 4d4.

### Level 6: Reef Denizen
At 6th level, when you conjure a reef with Coral Calling, you can expend another use of your Wild Shape to conjure a creature of the reef to populate it. The creature can be any beast with a swim speed that you can transform into with your Wild Shape into, such as a reef shark, giant crab, or giant sea horse. The creature appears in an unoccupied space within the reef, and remains in the reef until the reef crumbles, or until it is reduced to 0 hit points, upon which it disappears.

A creature you conjure in this way can breathe air and water, has a flying speed equal to its swimming speed, and appears with temporary hit points equal to twice your druid level. It can't leave the reef, either willingly or by being moved, and stops at the edge of the reef if it is moved against its will.

The creature obeys your telepathic commands (no action required by you), and shares your initiative in combat, but takes its turn immediately after yours. It can use your spell attack modifier in place of its own modifier for weapon attacks, and its natural weapons count as magical for the purpose of overcoming resistance and immunity to nonmagical attacks and damage.

At 14th level, you can conjure two creatures instead of one when you use this feature. The beasts you summon can be the same type of creature, or two different ones. 

### Level 10: Breath of the Sea
At 10th level, like a coral reef sifting through the ocean currents, you can filter harmful magic into healing energy. As a reaction when you see a creature within 30 feet of you casting a spell, you can make an ability check using your Wisdom to attempt to counteract the spell. The DC of this check equals 10 + the spell's level. On a success, the spell fails and has no effect, and up to three creatures of your choice within 30 feet of you regain hit points equal to twice the spell's level.

Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest.

### Level 14: Ageless Reef
At 14th level, your reefs stand as ageless as the ocean itself. When a reef you create with the Coral Calling feature would crumble, you can choose to have it remain in place instead, centered on the space you currently occupy. If you do this while you already have an ageless reef, the older one is destroyed. An ageless reef also crumbles if struck by a disintegrate spell.

An ageless reef otherwise functions identically to a normal reef you create, and a reef denizen you conjure remains until it is reduced to 0 hit points or the reef is destroyed. Additionally, whenever a creature finishes a long rest in an ageless reef, it gains temporary hit points equal to your druid level.</description>
  </element>
  <element name="Barrier" type="Archetype" source="ABYSS" id="ID_ABYSS_ARCH_fighter_Barrier">
    <supports>Martial Archetype</supports>
    <description>Barrier (ABYSS)

### Level 3: Barrier
Warriors who draw power from the tropical waters, Barriers harness the primal magic of the reef to don a spiked armor made of living creatures. Because of their connection to the natural world and potent martial prowess, Barriers are commonly fielded as champions and defenders among coastal cultures for their unbreakable endurance and ability to defend their companions.

### Level 3: Mantle of Coral
Upon taking this archetype at 3rd level, you can use a bonus action on your turn to create a suit of magical living armor around you, which lasts for 1 minute. You can create this armor on top of any existing armor you are wearing. While you have this armor, you gain the following benefits:

Your AC can't be less than 16.
If a creature within 5 feet of you hits you with a melee attack, the creature takes 1d4 piercing damage. This damage counts as magical for the purpose of overcoming resistance and immunity to nonmagical attacks and damage. The first time a creature takes this damage on a turn, its speed is reduced by 10 feet until the end of its next turn.

You can use this feature twice, and regain all expended uses of it when you finish a short or long rest.

### Level 3: Expel Toxin
Also at 3rd level, you take on the natural healing properties of coral, and can use it to expel yourself of poisons. When you regain hit points using your Second Wind feature while your Mantle of Coral is active, your armor deals an additional 1d6 poison damage until the start of your next turn, and you become cured of one disease or poison affecting you.

### Level 7: Fed by the Sun
At 7th level you can draw upon the light of the sun to nourish and sustain yourself. If you spend 1 hour in bright sunlight, you regain hit points equal to your Constitution modifier (minimum of 1 hit point), and gain enough nourishment to sustain yourself for one day.

### Level 10: Bristling Defense
Starting at 10th level, when a creature within 5 feet of you that you can see hits you with a melee attack while your Mantle of Coral is active, you can use your reaction to conjure bristling spines from your armor. You halve the attack's damage against you, and the attacker takes additional damage from your armor equal to your fighter level.

### Level 15: Frenzied Swarm
Beginning at 15th level, you can manifest creatures of the reef from your living armor to aid you in battle. As an action while your Mantle of Coral is active, you can conjure a swarm of quippers, which appears in your space (the DM has the creature's game statistics).

When conjured in this way, the swarm can breathe air and water, has a flying speed equal to its swimming speed, and appears with temporary hit points equal to twice your fighter level. Additionally, the swarm adds your Constitution modifier to attack and damage rolls it makes, and its attacks count as magical for the purpose of overcoming resistance and immunity to nonmagical attacks and damage. When the swarm deals damage to a creature, the creature's movement speed is reduced by 10 feet until the end of the creature's next turn.

The swarm obeys your verbal commands (no action required by you), and shares your initiative in combat, but takes its turn immediately after yours. The swarm disappears when it drops to 0 hit points or when your Mantle of Coral ends.

Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest.

### Level 18: Barrier Reef
At 18th level, your Mantle of Coral increases in potency and protective power. When you activate your Mantle of Coral, you gain temporary hit points equal to your fighter level, which last until your Mantle of Coral ends. Additionally, the piercing damage from your armor increases to 2d4, and a creature that takes this damage has its movement speed reduced to 0 feet until the end of its next turn.</description>
  </element>
  <element name="Way of the Four Elements (Expanded)" type="Archetype" source="ABYSS" id="ID_ABYSS_ARCH_monk_Way_of_the_Four_Elements_Expanded_">
    <supports>Monastic Tradition</supports>
    <description>Four Elements (Expanded) (ABYSS)

### Level 3: Elemental Disciplines (Expanded)
The following elemental disciplines are also available to you.

You can spend 5 ki points to cast steam vent.

You can spend 5 ki points to cast drown.

You can spend 4 ki points to cast aqueous form, targeting yourself. You can speak, attack, and cast spells as normal while transformed by the spell.

You can spend 2 ki points to cast riptide.

You can spend 6 ki points to cast instant iceberg.

You can spend 5 ki points to cast crushing depths.

You can spend 4 ki points to cast aqueous blast.

You can transfer the force of your strikes through water. Being underwater doesn't impose disadvantage on your unarmed strikes. Additionally, when you take the Attack action on your turn, you can spend 1 ki point to channel rippling energy around your form. For the rest of your turn, when you make an unarmed strike while you are within 5 feet of a body of water, you can choose a point within 30 feet of you that is within the same body of water. The attack is made as if you were at the chosen point, but you must use your own senses. When you hit a creature with such an attack, you can spend 1 ki point to attempt to push the target away. It must succeed on a Strength saving throw or be pushed up to 15 feet away from the point you chose.

You can spend 2 ki points to cast waterspout.

You can spend 4 ki points to cast geyser.

You can spend 3 ki points to cast crashing wave.

You can spend 3 ki points to cast freeze.</description>
  </element>
  <element name="Oath of Leadership" type="Archetype" source="ABYSS" id="ID_ABYSS_ARCH_paladin_Oath_of_Leadership">
    <supports>Sacred Oath</supports>
    <description>Leadership (ABYSS)

### Level 3: Oath of Leadership
Paladins who swear the Oath of Leadership reject lofty idealism and swear a personal commitment to those under their charge. Whether they be sea captains, military officers, or mercenary leaders, these knights believe that command is a sacred contract of service and not a means to an end. Their oath bids them to protect, guide, and do right by those that would follow them.

### Level 3: Tenets of Leadership
The tenets of the Oath of Leadership demands a paladin do right by those who they are responsible for.

 You are in service of those who follow you, and you bear responsibility for the actions of your followers.

 A leader's duty is to chart a path forward. Be thoughtful, but decisive. Determine the necessary steps and follow through to the end.

 The strength of many exceeds the strength of an individual. Bring people together toward a shared goal.

 Never give an order that you yourself would not follow.

### Level 3: Oath Spells
You gain oath spells at the paladin levels listed.

### Level 3: Channel Divinity
When you take this oath at 3rd level, you gain the following two Channel Divinity options.

 As a bonus action, you can use your Channel Divinity to call out to one creature you can see within 60 feet of you. If it can hear you, the creature can use its reaction to take the Attack (one weapon attack only), Dash, Dodge, or Use an Object action.

The number of creatures you can call out to when you use this Channel Divinity increases when you reach higher levels in this class, to two creatures at 7th level, three creatures at 15th level, and four creatures at 20th level.

 When you succeed on a saving throw against an effect that targets at least one other creature within 30 feet of you, you can use your reaction to use your Channel Divinity to choose a number of creatures up to your Charisma modifier (minimum of 1 creature) that you can see within 30 feet of you. If a chosen creature can see or hear you, it automatically succeeds its the saving throw against the triggering effect. You can choose to use this Channel Divinity after all the saving throws are rolled, but before the outcomes are determined.

### Level 7: Aura of Morale
Starting at 7th level, you radiate an aura of confidence that inspires those who follow you. When you score a critical hit or reduce a creature to 0 hit points, you can choose any number of creatures other than yourself within 10 feet of you. If a chosen creature can see or hear you, it gains temporary hit points equal to your Charisma modifier (minimum of 1 hit point), which last for 1 minute. While a creature has these hit points, it has advantage on attack rolls and ability checks.

At 18th level, the range of this aura increases to 30 feet.

### Level 15: Aegis of Trust
Starting at 15th level, those who follow you are protected by their trust in you. While a creature has temporary hit points granted by you, it has resistance to all damage.

### Level 20: Commanding Presence
At 20th level, you can manifest divine power to become an avatar of unquestionable authority. You can use your action to gain the following benefits for 1 minute:

You can cause your voice to boom up to ten times as loud as normal and be audible from up to 1 mile away.
When you deal damage to a creature with your Divine Smite, you can mark it for your allies to strike down. Until the start of your next turn, the creature takes an additional 1d8 radiant damage whenever it is hit by an attack.
You can cast command as a bonus action on your turn, without expending a spell slot.

Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest.</description>
  </element>
  <element name="Stormcaller" type="Archetype" source="ABYSS" id="ID_ABYSS_ARCH_ranger_Stormcaller">
    <supports>Ranger Archetype</supports>
    <description>Stormcaller (ABYSS)

### Level 3: Stormcaller
Experts in fighting in strong winds and heavy rain, Stormcallers draw their power from the rolling clouds and shifting skies. Able to manipulate the weather to their advantage, Stormcallers strike with the might of a hurricane, fracturing and blowing away their adversaries with bursts of windy magic and whirling blades.

### Level 3: Stormcaller Magic
Starting at 3rd level, you learn the druidcraft cantrip, and you learn an additional spell when you reach certain levels in this class, as shown in the Stormcaller Spells table. These spell count as ranger spells for you, but don't count against the number of ranger spells you know.

For players who don't have access to Xanathar's Guide to Everything, the following lines in the Stormcaller Spells table can be replaced:

### Level 3: Gale Step
Starting at 3rd level, you can channel the power of the wind into your own movements and attacks. When you move for the first time on your turn, you can double your speed until the end of the turn. If you move at least 10 feet straight toward a target and then hit it with a weapon attack before the end of the turn, the attack deals an extra 1d8 thunder damage. When you reach 11th level in this class, the extra damage increases to 2d8.

Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you move 0 feet on one of your turns.

### Level 3: Rain Cloak
At 3rd level, you learn to cloak yourself under cover of rain. While in light or heavy precipitation, you can use a bonus action on your turn to turn invisible until the start of your next turn, or until you attack, make a damage roll, or force someone to make a saving throw. Additionally, you don't have disadvantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks made when observing areas that are lightly obscured by heavy rain, falling snow, mist, or other water-based phenomena.

### Level 7: Darken Skies
At 7th level, you gain the ability to draw storm clouds overhead. If you are able to see the sky when you finish a short or long rest, you can cause dark clouds to form in a 1-mile radius directly above you. These dark clouds count as stormy conditions for the purpose of spells such as call lightning and the weather in the area changes to light rain or light snow.

If it is already lightly raining or lightly snowing when you use this feature, you can instead cause the weather in the area to worsen, turning light precipitation into heavy precipitation.

Changes in weather caused by this feature persist for a number of hours equal to your ranger level or until dispersed naturally or by magic.

### Level 11: Cyclone Burst
Beginning at 11th level, you can unleash a vicious cyclone of winds around you. When you move for the first time on your turn while using your Gale Step feature, you can force each creature within 10 feet of you to make a Strength saving throw against your ranger spell save DC. On a failed save, a creature takes 2d8 thunder damage and is pushed up to 10 feet away from you and knocked prone. This wind also blows away any smoke, mist, or fog in the area.

### Level 15: Shielded by Wind and Rain
At 15th level, you can bend the winds around you into a barrier against arrows and other missiles. While you aren't incapacitated, you have half cover against ranged attacks. Additionally, when a creature you can see makes a ranged attack against a target within 30 feet of you, you can use your reaction to grant the target half cover against the attack.

If you are standing in light or heavy precipitation, both instances of half cover become three-quarters cover.</description>
  </element>
  <element name="Marauder" type="Archetype" source="ABYSS" id="ID_ABYSS_ARCH_rogue_Marauder">
    <supports>Roguish Archetype</supports>
    <description>Marauder (ABYSS)

### Level 3: Marauder
Trained in the use of all sorts of weaponry and with a keen eye for treasure, your skills as a Marauder make you a terror wherever there is something of value ripe for the taking. These warriors trade deceit and precise maneuvers for pure power and brutal efficiency.

Marauders may travel the land as mounted raiders, or pillage the coasts on fast longships, making use of mobility and brutality to always strike where the rewards are greatest. Many pirates, raiders, and bandits follow this archetype, wandering land and sea in search of wealth or glory.

### Level 3: Marauder Training
When you choose this archetype at 3rd level, you gain proficiency with water vehicles, medium armor, shields, and martial weapons.

Additionally, you can apply the extra damage from your Sneak Attack to attacks made with any weapon you are proficient with, not just finesse or ranged weapons.

### Level 3: Smash and Grab
Also at 3rd level, you learn techniques to break down barriers that stand between you and your treasures. You can apply the extra damage from your Sneak Attack to any attack made against an object, even if you don't have advantage on the attack roll.

### Level 9: Brutal Coercion
At 9th level, you can use the bonus action granted by your Cunning Action to make a Charisma (Intimidation) check against a creature you can see within 30 feet of you, contested by the target's Wisdom (Insight) check, provided the target can see or hear you. If your check succeeds, the target drops the object you choose, which lands at its feet. If the creature is frightened, you automatically succeed on the check.

### Level 13: Frenzied Blows
Starting at 13th level, you learn to sacrifice precision in exchange for frenzied strikes. Once per turn when you take the Attack action and have advantage on an attack roll, you can forgo the advantage for that roll to make an additional weapon attack as part of the same action.

### Level 17: Terror Strike
Beginning at 17th level, you can turn the brutality of combat into a tool to terrify your foes. Once per turn when you hit a creature with a weapon attack, you can choose a creature that you can see within 30 feet of you. If the target can see you, it must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw or become frightened until the start of your next turn. The DC for this saving throw is equal to half the damage you dealt with the attack.</description>
  </element>
  <element name="Sunken Herald" type="Archetype" source="ABYSS" id="ID_ABYSS_ARCH_sorcerer_Sunken_Herald">
    <supports>Sorcerous Origin</supports>
    <description>Sunken Herald (ABYSS)

### Level 1: Sunken Herald
Your innate magic comes from strange undersea powers, spawned from creatures of the deep that lurk in furtive darkness. Krakens, merrow, sea hags and other marine horrors often abduct thralls from the surface, controlling them with hypnotic magic before discarding them and leaving them forever changed. You have a connection to one of these thralls—or could even be one of these thralls yourself—as the descendant of a deep scion, a child stolen by a sea hag, or someone anointed as an acolyte by a circle of kraken priests. Your inextricable connection to the depths warps your body and soul into strange, alien forms that terrify your terrestrial allies. Above all, the sea lures your mind, bringing you both calm and deep foreboding near the open waters.

Regardless of the source of your power, you fill those that lay eyes upon you with dread. The terrors of the depths and the horrors that live on the cold, black seafloor weave their way into your magic and your very body. Despite this, powerful Sunken Heralds tend to become the leaders of far-reaching cults and powerful secret societies.

### Level 1: Between Worlds
Your foul ancestry grants you abilities some consider unnatural. At 1st level, you learn Deep Speech, can breathe both air and water, and have a swim speed equal to your walking speed. Additionally, you can walk across the surface of liquid water as if it were harmless solid ground.

### Level 1: Malleable Flesh
At 1st level, you can cause the magic that flows through your veins to shift and change your body to suit your needs. When you cast a spell of 1st level or higher, you can modify your body in one of the ways listed below. If you cast a spell of 2nd level or higher, you can choose one additional feature for each slot level above 1st.

This change lasts for 1 minute, until you choose to use this feature again, or until you end it as a bonus action on your turn.

 Your arms and legs snap and stretch unnaturally, tripling in length. Your reach is increased to 10 feet on your turns, and your speed increases by 10 feet.

 The flesh of your hand swells and grows around one object that you're holding, mingling them together. You can't be disarmed of the item or drop it. If you are holding a structure or object too large for you to move, you can't be moved more than 5 feet away from that object.

 Thick, foul slime coats your skin. You have advantage on checks to avoid being grappled, and opportunity attacks against you are made at disadvantage.

 Your torso bursts into a web of blood vessels that anchors itself on structures and objects that aren't being worn or carried within 60 feet of you. Until this effect ends, you have advantage on checks and saves to avoid being knocked prone or moved unwillingly, and can use a bonus action to pull a Small or smaller object within range that isn't being worn or carried into your space. You can use a bonus action to focus your veins on a destination you choose within 60 feet of you. When you do so, the veins can fasten themselves securely to an object at that point, unfasten themselves, or spread evenly around you again.

 Your nails lengthen and sharpen into thin, translucent spindles, which you can use to make unarmed strikes. If you hit with them, you deal magical slashing damage equal to 1d8 + your Strength modifier.

 Corrosive brine drips from your hands, which become pitted and blackened. Your attacks and spells deal double damage against objects.

### Level 6: Weird Reconstruction
At 6th level, the bizarre biology that gave you life allows you to reform your body in horrific ways. When you take damage, you can use your reaction to warp your flesh back into shape. You gain temporary hit points equal to your sorcerer level, and if the source of damage was a creature, it must make a Wisdom saving throw against your sorcerer spell save DC. On a failed save, the target is frightened of you until the end of your next turn.

You can use this feature a number of times equal to your Charisma modifier (a minimum of once). You regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.

### Level 14: Monstrous Mass
At 14th level, your contorting, inhuman body terrifies and disorients your enemies. When you activate Malleable Flesh by casting a spell of 6th level or higher, each creature of your choice that is within 60 feet of you must make a Wisdom saving throw against your sorcerer spell save DC. On a failed save, a target is frightened of you until your transformation ends. While transformed in this way, frightened creatures have disadvantage on saving throws against your spells.

### Level 18: Pelagic Nightmare
Starting at 18th level, you can spend 5 sorcery points as an action to temporarily manifest images of an ancient, sunken city around yourself for 1 minute. All light within 120 feet of you is reduced to dim light, and creatures of your choice must use their swimming speed to move through the area, rather than their walking speed, and can't benefit from cover. When you create this effect, you can designate any number of creatures you can see to be unaffected by the visions of ocean depths. When a designated creature casts a spell or makes an attack while in the area, it can treat any point within 120 feet of you as the origin of the effect, as though it were standing in that space.</description>
  </element>
  <element name="Treasure Bound" type="Archetype" source="ABYSS" id="ID_ABYSS_ARCH_sorcerer_Treasure_Bound">
    <supports>Sorcerous Origin</supports>
    <description>Treasure Bound (ABYSS)

### Level 1: Treasure Bound
One of your ancestors left behind a vast fortune, stowed away in some hidden corner of the world, and protected it from would-be thieves and treasure hunters through layer upon layer of wards and curses. The magic of your ancestor's treasure has seeped into your bloodline, manifesting itself within you as arcane power that shimmers like gold, both a blessing and a curse.

Whether they were a canny noble, a daring pirate, or a hoarding dragon, the magic that your ancestor imbued within their hidden treasure is irrevocably bound to you, allowing you to reach into their hoard and temporarily pluck from it objects of incredible variety and value.

### Level 1: Manifest Treasure
At 1st level, you can pull gleaming treasure from your hoard to aid you in your adventures. As a bonus action on your turn, you can summon a nonmagical object worth a number of gold pieces no more than 50 × your sorcerer level. The object can be an art object, gemstone, trinket, weapon, shield, suit of armor, or piece of adventuring gear of your choice, so long as it isn't a piece of adventuring gear that is consumed when used (see chapter 5, "Equipment," in the Player's Handbook and chapter 7, "Treasure," in the Dungeon Master's Guide for options). Beyond the object's basic characteristics, you determine its appearance.

If the object is a weapon, shield, or suit of armor, you can choose to don or wield it as part of summoning it, and are proficient with it while you wield or wear it. Otherwise, it appears in your empty hand.

If an object conjured with this feature is consumed as the material component of a spell, it instead immediately disappears and the spell fails.

The object disappears after 1 minute, if you use this feature again, or if you dismiss it as a bonus action on your turn. You can use an action while you are touching the object to prevent it from disappearing for 1 minute.

### Level 1: All that Glitters
Also at 1st level, you can attempt to entrance a creature by appealing to its greed. When a creature you can see targets you with an attack or harmful spell, you can use your reaction to cause yourself to momentarily shine as if made of gold. The target must make a Wisdom saving throw against your sorcerer spell save DC. On a failed save, the creature becomes charmed by you until the end of your next turn, and must choose a new target or lose the attack or spell. While the creature is charmed in this way, it can't willingly move away from you.

You can use this feature a number of times equal to your Charisma modifier (a minimum of once). You regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.

### Level 6: Ethereal Vault
Beginning at 6th level, you can add valuable items you come across to your bound hoard, transporting and storing them into a pocket dimension. You can bond with an object you are touching by performing a ritual over the course of 1 hour, which can be done during a short rest. The object must either be a magic item or a nonmagical one worth at least 50 gold pieces. At the end of the ritual, you magically bond to the object and store it in a pocket dimension, which can hold up to 500 pounds, not exceeding a volume of 64 cubic feet. The ritual fails if you attempt to bond with an object that would overload the pocket dimension. While you are bound to an object, you can summon or dismiss it as a bonus action on your turn. It otherwise behaves as if summoned by your Manifest Treasure feature.

When you summon an object, you can choose to sever your bond to it. If you die, all of your bonds are severed, and the contents of the pocket dimension appear at your feet.

Additionally, you can spend 1 sorcery point when you use your Manifest Treasure feature to summon two objects at once. This number increases to three objects at 14th level and to four objects at 18th level.

### Level 14: Price of Greed
Beginning at 14th level, you learn the bestow curse spell, which counts as a sorcerer spell for you but doesn't count against your number of sorcerer spells you know.

As an action, you can touch an object and cast bestow curse on it. When you cast the spell in this way, it has no effect, and the spell is instead stored in the object until it is triggered or the spell ends. You must maintain concentration of the spell as normal if it requires concentration. You can designate any creatures you choose when you cast the spell, and the spell ignores them. When a creature not designated by you comes into contact with the object, it becomes targeted by the bestow curse spell stored in the object. If the object is a weapon, a creature becomes targeted by the spell if it is hit by an attack made with it. If the object is a shield or suit of armor that is being worn, a creature becomes targeted by the spell if it grapples its wearer or hits its wearer with a melee attack while within 5 feet of it.

You can only store a bestow curse spell in one object at a time. If you use this feature to store the spell in a second object, the spell stored in the first object ends.

### Level 18: Boundless Hoard
At 18th level, you can manifest vast treasures from those bound to you, raining them down upon your foes. As a bonus action on your turn, you can spend up to 5 sorcery point to conjure objects from your bound hoard, choosing from the objects available to you from your Manifest Treasure feature, and send them flying toward targets within 60 feet of you. You conjure one object per sorcery point spent, and can direct the objects at one target or several. Make a ranged spell attack for each object. On a hit, the target takes 2d8 force damage, and the object disappears.</description>
  </element>
  <element name="The Ghost Ship" type="Archetype" source="ABYSS" id="ID_ABYSS_ARCH_warlock_The_Ghost_Ship">
    <supports>Otherworldly Patron</supports>
    <description>Ghost Ship (ABYSS)

### Level 1: The Ghost Ship
You have made a pact with one of the lost ships crewed by listless dead that wander the seas. Sailors see these ships, such as the Flying Dutchman or Ship of One Hundred, as portents of doom, but even in death the cursed crew and their damned captain retain a fierce love of their vessel—the only home known to their forsaken souls. The loyalty shared by captain, crew, and ship pierces the veil between life and death and grant you your power. Whether you are a member of the drowned crew sent alone on a mission, a stowaway who chose an unfortunate vessel, or a sailor rescued from a watery grave, the dead men follow you everywhere—and the spectral ship itself powers your spells.

### Level 1: Expanded Spell List
The Ghost Ship lets you choose from an expanded list of spells when you learn a warlock spell. The following spells are added to the warlock spell list for you.

### Level 1: Haunted Hull
Starting at 1st level, you can manifest phantasmal fragments of the Ghost Ship on the battlefield, crewed by ethereal spirits with wispy skeletons and translucent flesh. You can use an action to manifest parts of the ship as one of the following effects. Once you manifest one of these effects, you can't use this feature again until you finish a short or long rest.

 You manifest a single undead lookout, which hovers up to 120 feet directly above you for 1 minute. While you aren't deafened, you know the location of every creature within 120 feet of you, including those that are hidden, invisible, or on the Ethereal Plane.

 You manifest spectral ropes, which lash out at a creature you can see within 60 feet of you. The target must succeed on a Dexterity saving throw against your warlock spell save DC or be restrained by ropes for 1 minute. A restrained creature can use its action to make a Strength check against your warlock spell save DC, freeing itself and destroying the ropes on a success.

 You manifest the tattered masts of the ghostly ship, which drain the wind out of your enemies' sails. Your speed increases by 10 feet for 1 minute, and each creatures of your choice within 30 feet of you must make a Wisdom saving throw against your warlock spell save DC. On a failed save, its speed is reduced by 10 feet for 1 minute.

### Level 1: Learn from our Mistakes
At 1st level, the crewmen of the Ghost Ship pass some of their nautical knowledge on to you. You gain proficiency with navigator's tools and vehicles (water). Additionally, you can determine whether or not an item is cursed by spending 1 minute examining it.

### Level 6: Bosun's Lash
Beginning at 6th level, you can conjure a ghastly officer as a bonus action on your turn, who cracks a spectral whip at a willing creature of your choice within 15 feet of you before vanishing. The creature takes 1d4 force damage and gains a bonus equal to the damage taken to the next attack roll or ability check it makes before the start of your next turn.

### Level 10: Eternal Sailor
Starting at 10th level, you gain some traits of the vessel's ghostly crew. You gain the following benefits:

You are immune to poison and disease.
You no longer need to breathe.
You can sink in water at a rate of 60 feet per round, moving at the start of your turn.
You suffer no penalties to your movement or attacks from being underwater.

### Level 14: Skeleton Crew
At 14th level, you gain the ability to summon the entire crew to fight at your side. As an action, you can manifest a skeleton crew in an unoccupied space that you can see within 60 feet of you. The crew is friendly to you and follow your commands. Roll initiative for the crew, which has its own turn.

The skeleton crew disappears after 1 hour, when it drops to 0 hit points, or if you lose your concentration (as if you were concentrating on a spell). The skeleton crew's can use your warlock spell attack bonus and spell save DC in place of its own attack bonuses or save DCs.

Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest.</description>
  </element>
  <element name="School of Hydromancy" type="Archetype" source="ABYSS" id="ID_ABYSS_ARCH_wizard_School_of_Hydromancy">
    <supports>Arcane Tradition</supports>
    <description>Hydromancy (ABYSS)

### Level 2: School of Hydromancy
As a member of the School of Hydromancy, you focus your study on magic that conjures and manipulates water. Though detractors of this school believe it to be an overly specialized area of study, hydromancy spells actually cover a wide selection of the eight traditional schools of magic. Hydromancers can use their spells to protect themselves and their allies, disperse and destroy their foes, or do many other tasks. Though members of this school are most often sought out by shipmasters or the lords of coastal settlements, they can be found working in an array of diverse occupations and in varied environments.

### Level 2: Hydromancy Savant
Beginning when you select this school at 2nd level, the gold and time you must spend to copy a spell that has the hydromancy tag into your spellbook is halved.

### Level 2: Aqueous Magic
Beginning at 2nd level, you can use magic leftover from your spells to conjure shallow pools of water. When you cast a spell of 1st level or higher using a spell slot, you can create one of these pools centered on a point on the ground that you can see within 30 feet of you. The pool manifests as a 1-inch-deep layer of water on the ground. It covers a 10-foot-radius for a 1st-level spell slot, and the radius increases by 5 feet for each slot level higher than 1st. The pool lasts for 1 minute, and stays in the location it was created for its entire duration, even on inclines or if subjected to strong winds.

If you start your turn standing in one of these pools of water, your speed is increased by 10 feet until the end of the turn. Also, while standing in one of these pools you are aware of any hidden or invisible creatures within 10 feet of you that are also standing within a pool conjured by this feature.

These pools count as bodies of water for your hydromancy spells, and pools that intersect count as the same body of water.

### Level 6: Watery Transposition
Starting at 6th level, when you cast a hydromancy spell of 1st level or higher and utilize the spell's hydromancy radius, you can choose to teleport to the point that you chose to cast the spell from. You teleport after the spell is cast.

You can use this feature twice. You regain all expended uses of it when you finish a short or long rest.

### Level 10: Elemental Command
At 10th level, you add the conjure elemental spell to your spellbook if it is not there already. If the spell is already in your spellbook, you add a wizard spell of your choice with the hydromancy tag instead. You can cast conjure elemental without expending a spell slot. When you do so, you summon a water weird rather than one of the spell's normal options (the DM has the creature's game statistics). The water weird can be bound to one of the pools you create with your Aqueous Magic feature, or bound to a regular body of water.

Once you cast conjure elemental in this way, you can't do so again until you finish a long rest, though you can still cast it normally using an available spell slot.

If you use conjure elemental to summon a water elemental or water weird, the spell has a casting time of 1 action, and the summoned creature disappears if your concentration is broken rather than becoming hostile to you.

### Level 14: One with the Waves
Starting at 14th level, the pools created with your Aqueous Magic feature become imbued with stronger magic. While you stand within one of these pools, you gain the following benefits:

You gain a +2 bonus to your AC.
You gain advantage on Constitution saving throws.
You are aware of any hidden or invisible creatures that are also standing within a pool, regardless of distance.</description>
  </element>
</elements>